DAVID SONTAG: So I'll
begin today's lecture
by giving a brief recap
of risk stratification.
We didn't get to finish talking
survival modeling on Thursday,
and so I'll go a little
bit more into that,
and I'll answer some
of the questions that
arose during our discussions
and on Piazza since.
And then the vast majority
of today's lecture we'll
be talking about a new topic--
in particular, physiological
time series modeling.
I'll give two examples of
physiological time series
modeling-- the first one
coming from monitoring patients
in intensive care units,
and the second one
asking a very different
type of question--
that of diagnosing patients'
heart conditions using EKGs.
And both of these
correspond to readings
that you had for
today's lecture,
and we'll go into much
more depth in these--
of those papers today, and
I'll provide much more color
around them.
So just to briefly remind you
where we were on Thursday,
we talked about how one could
formalize risk stratification
instead of as a classification
problem of what would happen,
let's say, in some
predefined time period,
rather thinking about
risk stratification
as a regression question,
or regression task.
Given what you know about
a patient at time zero,
predicting time to event--
so for example, here the
event might be death, divorce,
college graduation.
And patient one-- that event
happened at time step nine.
Patient two, that event
happened at time step 12.
And for patient four, we don't
know when that event happened,
because it was censored.
In particular, after
time step seven,
we no longer get to view
any of the patients' data,
and so we don't know when
that red dot would be--
sometime in the future or never.
So this is what we mean by
right censor data, which
is precisely what survival
modeling is aiming to solve.
Are there questions
about this setup first?
AUDIENCE: You flipped the x on--
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah,
I realized that.
I flipped the x and the o
in today's presentation,
but that's not relevant.
So f of t is the
probability of death,
or the event occurring
at time step t.
And although in this
slide I'm showing it
as an unconditional
model, in general,
you should think about this
as a conditional density.
So you might be conditioning
on some covariates or features
that you have for that
patient at baseline.
And very important
for survival modeling
and for the next
things I'll tell
you are the survival function,
to note it as capital S of t.
And that's simply 1 minus the
cumulative density function.
So it's the probability
that the event occurring,
which is time--
which is denoted
here as capital T,
occurs greater
than some little t.
So it's this function,
which is simply
given to you by
the integral from 0
to infinity of the density.
So in pictures,
this is the density.
On the x-axis is time.
The y-axis is the
density function.
And this black curve is
what I'm denoting as f of t.
And this white area is capital s
of c, the survival probability,
or survival function.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So I just
want to be clear.
So if you were to
integrate the entire curve,
[INAUDIBLE] by infinity you're
going to be [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: In the
way that I described it
to here, yes, because we're
talking about the time
to event.
But often we might be in
scenarios where the event may
never occur, and so that--
you can formalize that in
a couple of different ways.
You could put that at point
mass at s of infinity,
or you could simply say that
the integral from 0 to infinity
is some quantity less than 1.
And in the readings
that I'm referencing
in the very bottom of
those slides-- it shows you
how you can very easily
modify all of the frameworks
I'm telling you about here
to deal with that scenario
where the event may never occur.
But for the purposes
of my presentation,
you can assume that
the event will always
occur at some point.
It's a very minor modification
where you, in essence, divide
the densities by a constant,
which accounts for the fact
that it wouldn't integrate
to one otherwise.
Now, a key question
that has to be solved
when trying to use a parametric
approach to survivor modeling
is, what should that
f of t look like?
What should that density
function look like?
And what I'm showing you here
is a table of some very commonly
used density functions.
What you see in
these two columns--
on the right hand column is the
density function f of t itself.
Lambda denotes some
parameter of the model.
t is the time.
And on this second middle
column is the survival function.
So this is obtained for these
particular parametric forms
by an analytical solution
solving that integral from t
to infinity.
This is the analytic
solution for that.
And so these go by common
names of exponential,
weeble, log-normal, and so on.
And critically, all of
these have support only
on the positive real numbers,
because the event can ever
occur at negative time.
Now, we live in a
day and age where
we no longer have to make
standard parametric assumptions
for densities.
We could, for example, try
to formalize the density
as some output of some
deep neural network.
But if we don't use a
parametric approach,
so there are two ways
to try to do that.
One way to do that would
be to say that we're
going to model the post--
the distribution, f of t, as one
of these things, where lambda
or whatever the
parameters of distribution
are given to by the
output of, let's
say, a deep neural network
on the covariate x.
So that would be one approach.
A very different
approach would be
a non-parametric distribution
where you say, OK, I'm
going to define f of
t extremely flexibly,
not as one of these forms.
And there one runs into a
slightly different challenge,
because as I'll show
you in the next slide,
to do maximum
likelihood estimation
of these distributions
from censor data,
one needs to get-- one needs
to make use of this survival
function, s of t.
And so if you're
f if t is complex,
and you don't have a nice
analytic solution for s of t,
then you're going to
have to somehow use
a numerical approximation
of s of t during limiting.
So it's definitely
possible, but it's going
to be a little bit more effort.
So now here's where I'm going
to get into maximum likelihood
estimation of these
distributions,
and to define for you
the likelihood function,
I'm going to break it down
into two different settings.
The first setting
is an observation
which is uncensored, meaning
we do observe when the event--
death, for example-- occurs.
And in that case, the
probability of the event--
it's very simple.
It's just probability of the
event occurring at capital--
at capital T, random
variable T, equals
a little t-- is just f or t.
Done.
However, what happens
if, for this data point,
you don't observe when the event
occurred because of censoring?
Well, of course, you could just
throw away that data point,
not use it in your
estimation, but that's
precisely what we mentioned
at the very beginning
of last week's lecture-- was
the goal of survival modeling
to not do that,
because if we did
that, it would introduce bias
into our estimation procedure.
So we would like to be able
to use that observation
that this data
point was censored,
but the only information we
can get from that observation
is that capital
T, the event time,
must have occurred
some time larger
than the observed-- the
time of censoring, which
is little t here.
So we don't know precisely
when capital T was, but we
know it's something larger than
the observed centering time
little of t.
And that, remember, is precisely
what the survival function
is capturing.
So for a censored
observation, we're
going to use capital S of
t within the likelihood.
So now we can then combine these
two for censored and uncensored
data, and what we get is the
following likelihood objective.
This is-- I'm showing you here
the log likelihood objective.
Recall from last week that
little b of i simply denotes
is this observation
censored or not?
So if bi is 1, it means
the time that you're given
is the time of the
censoring event.
And if bi is 0, it means
the time you're given
is the time that
the event occurs.
So here what we're going to do
is now sum over all of the data
points in your data
set from little i
equals 1 to little n of bi
times log of probability
under the censored model
plus 1 minus bi times log
of probability under
the uncensored model.
And so this bi is just going
to switch on which of these two
you're going to use for
that given data point.
So the learning objective for
maximum likelihood estimation
here is very similar
to what you're used to
in learning distributions
with the big difference
that, for censored
data, we're going
to use the survival function
to estimate its probability.
Are there any questions?
And this, of course,
could then be
optimized via your
favorite algorithm,
whether it be stochastic
gradient descent,
or second order
method, and so on.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: I have a
question about the a kind
of side project.
You mentioned that we
could use [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: Yes.
AUDIENCE: And then combine it
with the parametric approach.
DAVID SONTAG: Yes.
AUDIENCE: So is that
true that we just still
have the parametric
assumption that we kind of map
the input to the parameters?
DAVID SONTAG: Exactly.
That's exactly right.
So consider the following
picture where for--
this is time, t.
And this is f of t.
You can imagine
for any one patient
you might have a
different function.
You might-- but they might all
be of the same parametric form.
So they might be
like that, or maybe
they're shifted a little bit.
So you think about
each of these three
things as being from the
same parametric family
of distributions, but
with different means.
And in this case,
then the mean is
given to as the output of
the deep neural network.
And so that would be the
way it would be used,
and then one could just back
propagate in the usual way
to do learning.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Can you
repeat what b sub i is?
DAVID SONTAG: Excuse me?
AUDIENCE: Could you
repeat what b sub i is?
DAVID SONTAG: b sub i is just an
indicator whether the i-th data
point was censored
or not censored.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So [INAUDIBLE] equal
it's more a probability density
function [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID SONTAG: Cumulative
density function.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, but
[INAUDIBLE] probability.
No, for the [INAUDIBLE] it's
probability density function.
DAVID SONTAG Yes, so just to--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID SONTAG: Excuse me?
AUDIENCE: Will
that be any problem
to combine those
two types there?
DAVID SONTAG: That's
a very good question.
So the observation was that
you have two different types
of probabilities used here.
In this case, we're
using something
like the cumulative
density, whereas here we're
using the probability
density function.
The question was, are these
two on different scales?
Does it make sense
to combine them
in this type of linear fashion
with the same weighting?
And I think it does make sense.
So think about a setting where
you have a very small time
range.
You're not exactly sure
when this event occurs.
It's something in
this time range.
In the setting of
the censored data,
where that time range could
potentially be very large,
your model is providing--
your log probability
is somehow going
to be much more flat,
because you're covering
much more probability mass.
And so that
observation, I think,
intuitively is likely
to have a much--
a bit of a smaller effect on
the overall learning algorithm.
These observations-- you know
precisely where they are,
and so as you deviate from that,
you incur the corresponding log
loss penalty.
But I do think
that it makes sense
to have them in the same scale.
If anyone in the room has done
work with [INAUDIBLE] modeling
and has a different answer
to that, I'd love to hear it.
Not today, but maybe
someone in the future
will answer this
question differently.
I'm going to move on for now.
So the remaining question that
I want to talk about today
is how one evaluates
survival models.
So we talked about binary
classification a lot
in the context of
risk stratification
in the beginning, and we talked
about how area under the ROC
curve is one measure of
classification performance,
but here we're doing more--
something more akin to
regression, not classification.
A standard measure that's
used to measure performance
is known as the C-statistic,
or concordance index.
Those are one in the same--
and is defined as follows.
And it has a very
intuitive definition.
It sums over pairs
of data points
that can be compared
to one another,
and it says, OK, what
is the likelihood
of the event happening
for an event that
occurs before an event--
another event.
And what you want is that the
likelihood of the event that,
on average, in essence,
should occur later
should be larger than the event
that should occur earlier.
I'm going to first illustrate
it with this picture,
and then I'll work
through the math.
So here's the picture, and
then we'll talk about the math.
So what I'm showing you here
are every single observation
in your data set,
and they're sorted
by either the censoring
time or the event time.
So by black, I'm illustrating
uncensored data points.
And by red, I'm denoting
censored data points.
Now, here we see that
this data point--
the event happened before this
data point's censoring event.
Now, since this data
point was censored,
it means it's true event
time you could think about as
sometime into the far future.
So what we would want
is that the model
gives that the probability that
this event happens by this time
should be larger
than the probability
that this event
happens by this time,
because this actually
occurred first.
And these two are comparable
together-- to each other.
On the other hand, it
wouldn't make sense
to compare y2 and y4,
because both of these
were censored data
points, and we don't know
precisely when they occurred.
So for example, it could
have very well happened
that the event 2
happened after event 4.
So what I'm showing you here
with each of these lines
are the pairwise
comparisons that
are actually possible to make.
You can make pairwise
comparisons, of course,
between any pair of events
that actually did occur,
and you can make
pairwise comparisons
between censored events and
events that occurred before it.
Now, if you now look at this
formula, the formula in this
indicate-- this is looking
at an indicator of survival
functions between pairs of data
points, and which pairs of data
points?
It was precisely those
pairs of data points,
which I'm showing comparisons
of with these blue lines here.
So we're going to sum over i
such that bi is equal to 0,
and remember that means it
is an uncensored data point.
And then we look at--
we look at yi compared to
all other yj that's great--
that has a value greater than--
both censored and uncensored.
Now, if your data had no
sensor data points in it,
then you can verify that,
in fact, this corresponds--
so there's one other
assumption one has to make,
which is that--
suppose that your
outcome is binary.
And so if you might wonder
how you get a binary outcome
from this, imagine that
your density function
looked a little bit like this,
where it could occur either
at time 1 or time 2.
So something like that.
So if the event can
occur at only two times,
not a whole range
of times, then this
is analogous to
a binary outcome.
And so if you have
a binary outcome
like this and no censoring,
then, in fact, that C-statistic
is exactly equal to the
area under the ROC curve.
So that just connects it a
little bit back to things
we're used to.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Just to make
sure that I understand.
So y1 is going to be
we observed an event,
and y2 is going to be we
know that no event occurred
until that day?
DAVID SONTAG: Every dot
corresponds to one event,
either censored or not.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.
DAVID SONTAG: And
they're sorted.
In this figure, they're
sorted by the time
of either the censoring
or the event occurring.
So I talked to--
when I talked about
C-statistic, it--
that's one way to measure
performance of your survival
modeling, but you
might remember that I--
that when we talked about
binary classification,
we said how area
under there ROC curve
in itself is very
limiting, and so we
should think through
other performance
metrics of relevance.
So here are a few other
things that you could do.
One thing you could
do is you could
use the mean squared error.
So again, thinking about
this as a regression problem.
But of course, that
only makes sense
for uncensored data points.
So focus just in the
uncensored data points,
look to see how well
we're doing at predicting
when the event occurs.
The second thing one could
do, since you have the ability
to define the likelihood
of an observation,
censored or not censored,
one could hold out data,
and look at the held-out
likelihood or log likelihood
of that held-out data.
And the third thing
you could do is
you can-- after learning
using this survival modeling
framework, one could then turn
it into a binary classification
problem by, for
example, artificially
choosing time ranges, like
greater than three months is 1.
Less than three months is 0.
That would be one
crude definition.
And then once you've
done a reduction
to a binary
classification problem,
you could use all of
the existing performance
metrics they're used to thinking
about for binary classification
to evaluate the
performance there--
things like positive
predictive value, for example.
And you could, of course,
choose different reductions
and get different
performance statistics out.
So this is just a
small subset of ways
to try to evaluate
survivor modeling,
but it's a very,
very rich literature.
And again, on the
bottom of these slides,
I pointed you to
several references
that you could go
to to learn more.
The final comment
I wanted to make
is that I only told
you about one estimator
in today's lecture, and that's
known as the likelihood based
estimator.
But there is a whole
other estimation approach
for survival modelings, which
is very important to know about,
that are called partial
likelihood estimators.
And for those of you who have
heard of Cox proportional
hazards models-- and I
know they were discussed
in Friday's recitation--
that's an example
of a class of model
that's commonly used within this
partial likelihood estimator.
Now, at a very intuitive level,
what this partial likelihood
estimator is doing is it's
working with something
like the C-statistic.
So notice how the C-statistic
only looks at relative
orderings of events--
of their event occurrences.
It doesn't care about exactly
when the event occurred or not.
In some sense,
there's a constant.
There's-- in this
survival function,
which could be divided out from
both sides of this inequality,
and it wouldn't affect
anything about the statistic.
And so one could think
about other ways of learning
these models by
saying, well, we want
to learn a survival
function such
that it gets the ordering
correct between data points.
Now, such a survival function
wouldn't do a very good job.
There's no reason it would
do any good at getting
the precise time of
when an event occurs,
but if your goal were
to just figure out
what is the sorted order
of patients by risk
so that you're going to do an
intervention on the 10 most
risky people, then getting that
order incorrect is going to be
enough, and that's
precisely the intuition used
behind these partial
likelihood estimators--
so they focus on something
which is a little bit less
than the original
goal, but in doing
so, they can have much better
statistical complexity,
meaning the amount of
data they need in order
to fit this models well.
And again, this is
a very rich topic.
All I wanted to do is
give you a pointer to it
so that you can go read more
about it if this is something
of interest to you.
So now moving on
into the recap, one
of the most important points
that we discussed last week
was about non-stationarity.
And there was a question
posted to Piazza,
which was really interesting,
which is how do you actually
deal with non-stationarity.
And I spoke a lot
about it existing,
and I talked about
how to test for it,
but I didn't say what
to do if you have it.
So I thought this was such
an interesting question
that I would also talk about
it a bit during lecture.
So the short answer is, if
you have to have a solution
that you deploy
tomorrow, then here's
the hack that sometimes works.
You take your most recent data,
like the last three months'
data, and you hope
that there's not
much non-stationarity
within last three months.
You throw out all
the historical data,
and you just train using
the most recent data.
So a bit unsatisfying,
because you
might have now extremely
little data left to learn with,
but if you have enough volume,
it might be good enough.
But the real
interesting question
from a research perspective
is how could you optimally use
that historical data.
So here are three
different ways.
So one way has to
do with imputation.
Imagine that the way in which
your data was non-stationary
was because there
were, let's say,
parts of time when certain
features were just unavailable.
I gave you this example last
week of laboratory test results
across time, and I showed
you how there are sometimes
these really big
blocks of time where
no lab tests are available,
or very few are available.
Well, luckily we live in a world
with high dimensional data,
and what that means is there's
often a lot of redundancy
in the data.
So what you could imagine
doing is imputing features
that you observed
to be missing, such
that the missingness
properties, in fact,
aren't changing as much
across time after imputation.
And if you do that as
a pre-processing step,
it may allow you
to make use of much
more of the historical data.
A different approach, which
is intimately tied to that,
has to do with
transforming the data.
Instead of imputing
it, transforming it
into another representation
altogether, such that
that presentation is
invariant across time.
And here I'm giving
you a reference
to this paper by Ganin et al
from the Journal of Machine
Learning Research 2016,
which talks about how
to do domain and variant
learning of neural networks,
and that's one
approach to do so.
And I view those two as being
very similar-- imputation
and transformations.
A second approach is
to re-weight the data
to look like the current data.
So imagine that you
go back in time,
and you say, you know what?
I ICD-10 codes, for
some very weird reason--
this is not true, by the way--
ICD-10 codes in
this untrue world
happen to be used between
March and April of 2003.
And then they weren't
used again until 2015.
So instead of throwing away
all of the previous data,
we're going to
recognize that those--
that three month
interval 10 years ago
was actually drawn from a very
similar distribution as what
we're going to be
testing on today.
So we're going to weight those
data points up very much,
and down weight the
data points that are
less like the ones from today.
That's the intuition behind
these re-weighting approaches,
and we're going to talk
much more about that
in the context of
causal inference,
not because these two have
to do with each other,
but they have-- they end up
using a very similar technique
for how to deal with datas
that shift, or covariate shift.
And the final technique
that I'll mention
is based on online
learning algorithms.
So the idea there is that there
might be cut points, change
points across time.
So maybe the data looks one
way up until this change point,
and then suddenly
the data looks really
different until
this change point,
and then suddenly
the data looks very
different on into the future.
So here I'm showing you there
are two change points in which
data set shift happens.
What these online learning
algorithms do is they say,
OK, suppose we were
forced to make predictions
throughout this
time period using
only the historical
data to make predictions
at each point in time.
Well, if we could
somehow recognize
that there might
be these shifts,
we could design
algorithms that are going
to be robust to those shifts.
And then one could try to
analyze-- mathematically
analyze those algorithms
based on the amount of regret
they would have to, for example,
an algorithm that knew exactly
when those changes were.
And of course, we don't
know precisely when
those changes were.
And so there's a whole field of
algorithms trying to do that,
and here I'm just give me one
citation for a recent work.
So to conclude risk
stratification--
this is the last slide here.
Maybe ask your
question after class.
We've talked about
two approaches
for formalizing risk
stratification-- first
as binary classification.
Second as regression.
And in the regression
framework, one
has to think about
censoring, which is why
we call it survival modeling.
Second, in our examples,
and again in your homework
assignment that's
coming up next week,
we'll see that
often the variables,
the features that are most
predictive make a lot of sense.
In the diabetes case, we said--
we saw how patients having
comorbidities of diabetes,
like hypertension, or
patients being obese
were very predictive of
patients getting diabetes.
So you might ask yourself, is
there something causal there?
Are those features that are very
predictive in fact causing--
what's causing the patient
to develop type 2 diabetes?
Like, for example,
obesity causing diabetes.
And this is where I
want to caution you.
You shouldn't interpret these
very predictive features
in a causal fashion,
particularly
not when one starts to work
with high dimensional data,
as we do in this course.
The reason for that
is very subtle,
and we'll talk about that in
the causal inference lectures,
but I just wanted to
give you a pointer
now that you shouldn't
think about it in that way.
And you'll understand
why in just a few weeks.
And finally we talked about ways
of dealing with missing data.
I gave you one
feature representation
for the diabetes case,
which was designed
to deal with missing data.
It said, was there any
diagnosis code 250.01
in the last three months?
And if there was, you have a 1.
If you don't, 0.
So it's designed to
recognize that you
don't have information, perhaps,
for some large chunk of time
in that window.
But that missing data
could also be dangerous
if that missingness itself has
caused you to non-stationarity,
which is then going to result in
your test distribution looking
different from your
training distribution.
And that's where approaches
that are based on imputation
could actually be very valuable,
not because they improve
your predictive accuracy
when everything goes right,
but because they might improve
your predictive accuracy when
things go wrong.
And so one of your readings
for last week's lecture
was actually an example of
that, where they used a Gaussian
process model to impute much of
the missing data in a patient's
continuous vital
signs, and then they
used a recurrent neural
network to predict
based on that imputed data.
So in that case, there are
really two things going on.
First is this robustness
to data set shift,
but there's a
second thing, which
is going on as well,
which has to do
with a trade-off between
the amount of data you have
and the complexity of
the prediction problem.
By doing imputations,
sometimes you
make your problem
look a bit simpler,
and simpler algorithms might
succeed where otherwise they
would fail because not
having enough data.
And that's something
that you saw
in that last week's reading.
So I'm done with
risk stratification.
I'll take a one minute breather
for everyone in the room,
and then we'll start
with the main topic
of this lecture, which is
physiological time-series
modeling.
Let's say started.
So here's a baby that's
not doing very well.
This baby is in the
intensive care unit.
Maybe it was a premature infant.
Maybe it's a baby who
has some chronic disease,
and, of course, parents
are very worried.
This baby is getting
very close monitoring.
It's connected to lots
of different probes.
In number one here, it's
illustrating a three probe--
three lead ECG, which we'll be
talking about much more, which
is measuring its heart, how
the baby's heart is doing.
Over here, this number
three is something
attached to the baby's foot,
which is measuring its--
it's a pulse oximeter, which
is measuring the baby's oxygen
saturation, the amount
of oxygen in the blood.
Number four is a probe which
is measuring the baby's
temperature and so on.
And so we're really taking
really close measurements
of this baby, because
we want to understand
how is this baby doing.
We recognize that there might
be really sudden changes
in the baby's state
of health that we
want to be able to recognize
as early as possible.
And so behind the scenes,
next to this baby,
you'll, of course, have a
huge number of monitors,
each of the monitors showing
the readouts from each
of these different signals.
And this type of data is really
prevalent in intensive care
units, but you'll also
see in today's lecture
how some aspects of
this data are now
starting to make its way
to the home, as well.
So for example, EKGs are now
available on Apple and Samsung
watches to help understand--
help to help with
diagnosis of arrhythmias,
even for people at home.
And so from this
type of data, there
are a number of really important
use cases to think about.
The first one is to
recognize that often we're
getting really noisy
data, and we want to try
to infer the true signal.
So imagine, for example,
the temperature probe.
The baby's true
temperature might be 98.5,
but for whatever reason-- we'll
see a few reasons here today--
maybe you're getting
an observation of 93.
And you didn't know.
Is that actually the
true baby temperature?
In which case we--
it would be in a lot of trouble.
Or is that an anomalous reading?
So we like t be able to
distinguish between those two
things.
And in other cases, we are
interested in not necessarily
fully understanding what's going
on with the baby along each
of those axes, but we
just want to use that data
for predictive purposes,
for risk stratification,
for example.
And so the type of
machine learning approach
that we'll take here will depend
on the following three factors.
First, do we have
label data available?
For example, do we
know the ground truth
of what the baby's
true temperature was,
at least for a few of the
babies in the training set?
Second.
Do we have a good mechanistic
or statistical model
of how this data might
evolve across time?
We know a lot about
hearts, for example.
Cardiology is one of
those fields of medicine
where it's really well studied.
There are good
simulators of hearts,
and how they beat
across time, and how
that affects the electrical
stimulation across the body.
And if we have these
good mechanistic
or statistical
models, that can often
allow one to trade off not
having much label data,
or just not having
much data period.
And it's really
these three points
which I want to illustrate
the extremes of in today's
lecture--
what do you do when you
don't have much data,
and what you do
when-- what you can
do when you have a ton of data.
And I think it's going to
be really informative for us
as we go out into the world
and will have to tackle
each of those two settings.
So here's an example of two
different babies with very
different trajectories.
One in the x-axis here
is time in seconds.
The y-axis here--
I think seconds, maybe minutes.
The y-axis here is beats per
minute of the baby's heart
rate, and you see in
some cases it's really
fluctuating a lot up and down.
In some cases, it's sort of
going in a similar-- in one
direction, and in all cases,
the short term observations
are very different from the
long range trajectories.
So the first problem
that I want us
to think about is one
of trying to understand,
how do we deconvolve between the
truth of what's going on with,
for example, the
patient's blood pressure
or oxygen versus interventions
that are happening to them?
So on the bottom
here, I'm showing
examples of interventions.
Here in this oxygen
uptake, we notice
how between roughly 1,000
and 2,000 seconds suddenly
there's no signal whatsoever.
And that's an example of
what's called dropout.
Over here, we see a
different type of--
the effect of a
different intervention,
which is due to a
probe recalibration.
Now, at that time,
there was a drop out
followed by a sudden
change in the values,
and that's really happening
due to a recalibration step.
And in both of
these cases, what's
going on with the individual
might be relatively
constant across time,
but what's being observed
is dramatically affected
by those interventions.
So we want to ask
the question, can we
identify those
artifactual processes?
Can we identify that these
interventions were happening
at those points in time?
And then, if we
could identify them,
then we could potentially
subtract their effect out.
So we could impute the
data, which we know-- now
know to be missing, and then
have this much higher quality
signal used for some
downstream predictive purpose,
for example.
And the second reason why
this can be really important
is to tackle this problem
called alarm fatigue.
Alarm fatigue is one of the
most important challenges facing
medicine today.
As we get better and better
in doing risk stratification,
as we come up with more and
more diagnostic tools and tests,
that means these red flags
are being raised more and more
often.
And each one of these has some
associated false positive rate
for it.
And so the more tests you have--
suppose the false
positive rate is
kept constant-- the more tests
you have, the more likely
it is that the union
of all of those
is going to be some error.
And so when you're in
an intensive care unit,
there are alarms going
off all the time.
And something that happens
is that nurses end up
starting to ignore those
alarms, because so often
those alarms are
false positives,
are due to, for
example, artifacts
like what I'm showing you here.
And so if we had techniques,
such as the ones we'll
talk about right now,
which could recognize when,
for example, the sudden drop
in a patient's heart rate
is due to an artifact and not
due to the patient's true heart
rate dropping--
if we had enough
confidence in that--
in distinguishing
those two things,
then we might not decide
to raise that red flag.
And that might reduce the
amount of false alarms,
and that then might reduce
the amount of alarm fatigue.
And that could have a very
big impact on health care.
So the technique which
we'll talk about today
goes by the name of switching
linear dynamical systems.
Who here has seen
a picture like this
on-- this picture on
the bottom before.
About half of the room.
So for the other
half of the room,
I'm going to give
a bit of a recap
into probabilistic modeling.
All of you are now familiar
with general probabilities.
So you're used to thinking
about, for example,
univariate Gaussian
distributions.
We talked about how one
could model survival, which
was an example of
such a distribution,
but for today's
lecture, we're going
to be thinking now about
multivariate probability
distributions.
In particular, we'll be thinking
about how a patient's state--
let's say their true
blood pressure--
evolves across time.
And so now we're interested in
not just the random variable
at one point in time, but
that same random variable
at the second point in
time, third point in time,
fourth point in time, fifth
point in time, and so on.
So what I'm showing
you here is known
as a graphical model, also
known as a Bayesian network.
And it's one way of illustrating
a multivariate probability
distribution that has particular
conditional independence
properties.
Specifically, in
this model, one node
corresponds to one
random variable.
So this is describing a
joint distribution on x1
through x6, y1 through y6.
So it's this
multivariate distribution
on 12 random variables.
The fact that this
is shaded in simply
denotes that, at test time, when
we use these models, typically
these y variables are observed.
Whereas our goal is usually
to infer the x variables.
Those are typically unobserved,
meaning that our typical task
is one of doing posterior
inference to infer
the x's given the y's.
Now, associated with
this graph, I already
told you the nodes correspond
to random variables.
The graph tells us how is this
joint distribution factorized.
In particular, it's
going to be factorized
in the following way--
as the product over
random variables
of the probability of
the i-th random variable.
I'm going to use z to just
denote a random variable.
Think of z as the
union of x and y.
zi conditioned on the parents--
the values of the parents of zi.
So I'm going to assume
this factorization,
and in particular for this
graphical model, which
goes by the name
of a Markov model,
it has a very specific
factorization.
And we're just going to read
it off from this definition.
So we're going to go in
order-- first x1, then y1,
then x2, then y2,
and so on, which
is going based on
a root to children
transversal of this graph.
So the first random
variable is x1.
Second variable is y2, and
what are the parents of y--
sorry, what are
the parents of y1.
Everyone can say out loud.
AUDIENCE: x1.
DAVID SONTAG: x1.
So y1 in this factorization
is only going to depend on x1.
Next we have x2.
What are the parents of x2?
Everyone say out loud?
AUDIENCE: x1.
DAVID SONTAG: x1.
Then we have y2.
What are the parents of y2.
Everyone say out loud.
AUDIENCE: x2.
DAVID SONTAG: x2 and so on.
So this joint
distribution is going
to have a particularly
simple form, which
is given to by this
factorization shown here.
And this factorization
corresponds one to one
with the particular graph in
the way that I just told you.
And in this way, we can define
a very complex probability
distribution by a number of much
simpler conditional probability
distributions.
For example, if each of the
random variables were binary,
then to describe
probability of y1 given x1,
we only need two numbers.
For each value of
x1, either 0 or 1,
we give the probability
of y1 equals 1.
And then, of course, probably y1
equals 0 is just 1 minus that.
So we can describe that very
complicated joint distribution
by a number of much
smaller distributions.
Now, the reason why I'm
drawing it in this way
is because we're making some
really strong assumptions
about the temporal
dynamics in this problem.
In particular, the
fact that x3 only
has an arrow from
x2 and not from x1
implies that x3 is
conditionally independent of x1.
If you knew x2's value.
So in some sense, think
about this as cutting.
If you're to take
x2 out of the model
and remove all edges
incident on it,
then x1 and x3 are now
separated from one another.
They're independent.
Now, for those of you who
do know graphical models,
you'll recognize that that type
of independent statement that I
made is only true
for Markov models,
and the semantics
for Bayesian networks
are a little bit different.
But actually for this
model, it's-- they're one
and the same.
So we're going to make
the following assumptions
for the conditional
distributions shown here.
First, we're going to suppose
that xt is given to you
by a Gaussian distribution.
Remember xt-- t is
denoting a time step.
Let's say 3-- it only
depends in this picture--
the conditional
distribution only
depends on the previous
time step's value, x2,
or xt minus 1.
So you'll notice how
I'm going to say here
xt is going to
distribute as something,
but the only random
variables in this something
can be xt minus 1, according
to these assumptions.
In particular, we're
going to assume
that it's some Gaussian
distribution, whose mean is
some linear transformation
of xt minus 1,
and which has a fixed
covariance matrix q.
So at each step of this process,
the next random variable
is some random walk from
the previous random variable
where you're moving according
to some Gaussian distribution.
In a very similar
way, we're going
to assume that yt is drawn also
as a Gaussian distribution,
but now depending on xt.
So I want you to think
about xt as the true state
of the patient.
It's a vector that's
summarizing their blood
pressure, their
oxygen saturation,
a whole bunch of
other parameters,
or maybe even just one of those.
And y1 are the observations
that you do observe.
So let's say x1 is the
patient's true blood pressure.
y1 is the observed
blood pressure,
what comes from your monitor.
So then a reasonable
assumption would
be that, well, if
all this were equal,
if it was a true
observation, then
y1 should be very close to x1.
So you might assume that
this covariance matrix is--
the covariance is-- the
variance is very, very small.
y1 should be very close to x1
if it's a good observation.
And of course, if it's
a noisy observation--
like, for example, if the probe
was disconnected from the baby,
then y1 should have
no relationship to x1.
And that dependence on the
actual state of the world
I'm denoting here by these
superscripts, s of t.
I'm ignoring that right
now, and I'll bring that
in in the next slide.
Similarly, the relationship
between x2 and x1
should be one which captures
some of the dynamics
that I showed in the previous
slides, where I showed over
here now this is the patient's
true heart rate evolving
across time, let's say.
Notice how, if you
look very locally,
it looks like there are some
very, very big local dynamics.
Whereas if you
look more globally,
again, there's some smoothness,
but there are some-- again,
it looks like some random
changes across time.
And so those-- that
drift has to somehow
be summarized in this model
by that A random variable.
And I'll get into more detail
about that in just a moment.
So what I just showed
you was an example
of a linear dynamical
system, but it
was assuming that there were
none of these events happening,
none of these
artifacts happening.
The actual model
that we were going
to want to be able
to use then is
going to also
incorporate the fact
that there might be artifacts.
And to model that,
we need to introduce
additional random
variables corresponding to
whether those artifacts
occurred or not.
And so that's now this model.
So I'm going to let these S's--
these are other
random variables,
which are denoting
artifactual events.
They are also
evolving with time.
For example, if there's
artifactual factual event
at three seconds, maybe there's
also an artifactual event
at four seconds.
And we like to model the
relationship between those.
That's why you
have these arrows.
And then the way that we
interpret the observations
that we do get depends
on both the true value
of what's going on
with the patient
and whether there was an
artifactual event or not.
And you'll notice
that there's also
an edge going from
the artifactual events
to the true values
to note the fact
that those interventions
might actually
be affecting the patient.
For example, if you
give them a medication
to change their blood
pressure, then that procedure
is going to affect the next time
step's value of the patient's
blood pressure.
So when one wants
to learn this model,
you have to ask yourself,
what types of data
do you have available?
Unfortunately, it's very hard
to get data on both the ground
truth, what's going
on with the patient,
and whether these artifacts
truly occurred or not.
Instead, what we actually have
are just these observations.
We get these very noisy blood
pressure draws across time.
So what this paper does is
it uses a maximum likelihood
estimation approach,
where it recognizes
that we're going to be
learning from missing data.
We're going to explicitly
think of these x's and the s's
as latent variables.
And we're going to
maximize the likelihood
of the whole entire model,
marginalizing over x and s.
So just maximizing the marginal
likelihood over the y's.
Now, for those of you who have
studied unsupervised learning
before, you might recognize
that as a very hard learning
problem.
In fact, it's-- that
likelihood is non-convex.
And one could imagine all sorts
of a heuristics for learning,
such as gradient descent,
or, as this paper uses,
expectation maximization, and
because of that non-convexity,
each of these
algorithms typically
will only reach a local
maxima of the likelihood.
So this paper uses EM,
which intuitively iterates
between inferring those missing
variables-- so imputing the x's
and the s's given
the current model,
and doing posterior inference
to infer the missing
variables given the
observed variables, using
the current model.
And then, once you've
imputed those variables,
attempting to refit the model.
So that's called the
m-step for maximization,
which updates the model and
just iterates between those two
things.
That's one learning
algorithm which
is guaranteed to reach a
local maxima of the likelihood
under some regularity
assumptions.
And so this paper
uses that algorithm,
but you need to be
asking yourself,
if all you ever
observe are the y's,
then will this algorithm
ever recover anything
close to the true model?
For example, there
might be large amounts
of non-identifiability here.
It could be that you
could swap the meaning
of the s's, and you'd get a
similar likelihood on the y's.
That's where bringing in domain
knowledge becomes critical.
So this is going to be an
example where we have no label
data or very little label data.
And we're going to do
unsupervised learning
of this model, but
we're going to use
a ton of domain knowledge
in order to constrain
the model as much as possible.
So what is that
domain knowledge?
Well, first we're
going to use the fact
that we know that a true heart
rate evolves in a fashion that
can be very well modeled by
an autoregressive process.
So the autoregressive process
that's used in this paper
is used to model the
normal heart rate dynamics.
In a moment, I'll tell you how
to model the abnormal heart
rate observations.
And intuitively-- I'll
first go over the intuition,
then I'll give you the math.
Intuitively what it
does is it recognizes
that this complicated signal can
be decomposed into two pieces.
The first piece shown here
is called a baseline signal,
and that, if you
squint your eyes
and you sort or ignore the
very local fluctuations,
this is what you get out.
And then you can
look at the residual
of subtracting this signal,
subtracting this baseline
from the signal.
And what you get
out looks like this.
Notice here it's around 0 mean.
So it's a 0 mean signal with
some random fluctuations,
and the fluctuations
are happening here
at a much faster rate than--
and for the original baseline.
And so the sum of bt and
this residual is a very--
it looks-- is exactly equal
to the true heart rate.
And each of these two things
we can model very well.
This we can model by
a random walk with--
which goes very
slowly, and this we
can model by a random walk
which goes very quickly.
And that is exactly what I'm
now going to show over here
on the left hand side.
bt, this baseline
signal, we're going
to model as a Gaussian
distribution, which
is parameterized as a function
of not just bt minus 1,
but also bt minus
2, and bt minus 3.
And so we're going to be
taking a weighted average
of the previous few time steps,
where we're smoothing out,
in essence, the observation--
the previous few observations.
If you were to--
if you're being a
keen observer, you'll
notice that this is no
longer a Markov model.
For example, if this p1
and p2 are equal to 2,
this then corresponds to a
second order Markov model,
because each random variable
depends on the previous two
time steps of the Markov chain.
And so after-- so you would
model now bt by this process,
and you would
probably be averaging
over a large number
of previous time steps
to get this smooth property.
And then you'd model xt minus bt
by this autoregressive process,
where you might,
for example, just
be looking at just the
previous couple of time steps.
And you recognize
that you're just doing
much more random fluctuations.
And then-- so that's how one
would now model normal heart
rate dynamics.
And again, it's just--
this is an example of
a statistical model.
There is no
mechanistic knowledge
of hearts being
used here, but we
can fit the data of normal
hearts pretty well using this.
But the next question and
the most interesting one
is, how does one now
model artifactual events?
So for that, that's where some
mechanistic knowledge comes in.
So one models that
the probe dropouts
are given by recognizing
that, if a probe
is removed from the baby, then
there should no longer be--
or at least if you-- after
a small amount of time,
there should no longer
be any dependence
on the true value of the baby.
For example, the blood pressure,
once the blood pressure probe
is removed, is no longer
related to the baby's true blood
pressure.
But there might be some delay
to that lack of dependence.
And so-- and that is going
to be encoded in some domain
knowledge.
So for example, in
the temperature probe,
when you remove the temperature
probe from the baby,
it starts heating up again--
or it starts cooling, so
assuming that the ambient
temperature is cooler
than the baby's temperature.
So you take it off the baby.
It starts cooling down.
How fast does it cool down?
Well, you could assume
that it cools down
with some exponential decay
from the baby's temperature.
And this is something
that is very reasonable,
and you could
imagine, maybe if you
had label data for just
a few of the babies,
you could try to fit the
parameters of the exponential
very quickly.
And in this way, now, we
parameterize the conditional
distribution of the temperature
probe, given both the state
and whether the artifact
occurred or not,
using this very simple
exponential decay.
And in this paper, they give
a very similar type of--
they make similar types
of-- analogous types
of assumptions for all of
the other artifactual probes.
You should think about
this as constraining
these conditional distributions
I showed you here.
They're no longer allowed to
be arbitrary distributions,
and so that, when one does
now expectation maximization
to try to maximize the marginal
likelihood of the data,
you've now constrained
it in a way
that you hopefully are
moved on to identifyability
of the learning problem.
It makes all of the
difference in learning here.
So in this paper,
their evaluation
did a little bit of fine
tuning for each baby.
In particular, they assumed
that the first 30 minutes
near the start consists
of normal dynamics
so that's there
are no artifacts.
That's, of course,
a big assumption,
but they use that to try to
fine tune the dynamic model
to fine tune it for each
baby and for themselves.
And then they looked
at the ability
to try to identify
artifactual processes.
Now, I want to go a little
bit slowly through this plot,
because it's quite interesting.
So what I'm showing
you here is a ROC curve
of the ability to
predict each of the four
different types of artifacts.
For example, at any
one point in time,
was there a blood sample
being taken or not?
At any one point
in time, was there
a core temperature disconnect
of the core temperature probe?
And to evaluate it,
they're assuming
that they have some label data
for evaluation purposes only.
And of course, you want to be
at the very far top left corner
up here.
And what we're showing here
are three different curves--
the very faint
dotted line, which
I'm going to trace out with
my cursor, is the baseline.
Think of that as a
much worse algorithm.
Sorry.
That's that line over there.
Everyone see it?
And this approach are
the other two lines.
Now, what's differentiating
those other two lines
corresponds to the particular
type of approximate inference
algorithm that's used.
To do this posterior
inference, to infer
the true value of the x's
given your noisy observations
in the model given here is
actually a very hard inference
problem.
Mathematically, I
think one can show
that it's an NP-hard
computational problem.
And so they have to
approximate it in some way,
and they use two different
approximations here.
The first approximation
is based on what they're
calling a Gaussian
sum approximation,
and it's a deterministic
approximation.
The second approximation is
based on a Monte Carlo method.
And what you see here is that
the Gaussian sum approximation
is actually dramatically better.
So for example, in
this blood sample one,
that the ROC curve looks like
this for the Gaussian sum
approximation.
Whereas for the Monte
Carlo approximation,
it's actually
significantly lower.
And this is just to
point out that, even
in this setting, where
we have very little data,
we're using a lot of domain
knowledge, the actual details
of how one does the
math-- in particular,
the proximate
inference-- can make
a really big difference in the
performance of this system.
And so it's something
that one should really
think deeply about, as well.
I'm going to skip that
slide, and then just mention
very briefly this one.
This is showing an
inference of the events.
So here I'm showing you
three different observations.
And on the bottom here,
I'm showing the prediction
of when artifact-- two different
artifactual events happened.
And these predictions
were actually quite good,
using this model.
So I'm done with that
first example, and--
and the-- just to recap
the important points
of that example, it was that
we had almost no label data.
We're tackling this problem
using a cleverly chosen
statistical model with some
domain knowledge built in,
and that can go really far.
So now we'll shift gears to
talk about a different type
of problem involving
physiological data,
and that's of detecting
atrial fibrillation.
So what I'm showing you
here is an AliveCore device.
I own one of these.
So if you want to drop
by my E25 545 office,
you can-- you can
play around with it.
And if you attach it
to your mobile phone,
it'll show you your electric
conductance through your heart
as measured through
your two fingers
touching this device
shown over here.
And from that, one can try to
detect whether the patient has
atrial fibrillation.
So what is atrial fibrillation?
Good question.
It's [INAUDIBLE].
So this is from the
American Heart Association.
They defined atrial fibrillation
as a quivering or irregular
heartbeat, also
known as arrhythmia.
And one of the big
challenges is that it
could lead to blood clot,
stroke, heart failure, and so
on.
So here is how a
patient might describe
having atrial fibrillation.
My heart flip-flops,
skips beats,
feels like it's banging
against my chest wall,
particularly when I'm
carrying stuff up my stairs
or bending down.
Now let's try to look
at a picture of it.
So this is a normal heartbeat.
Hearts move-- pumping like this.
And if you were to
look at the signal
output of the EKG of
a normal heartbeat,
it would look like this.
And it's roughly corresponding
to the different--
the signal is corresponding
to different cycles
of the heartbeat.
Now for a patient who
has atrial fibrillation,
it looks more like this.
So much more obviously abnormal,
at least in this figure.
And if you look at the
corresponding signal,
it also looks very different.
So this is just to give you
some intuition about what
I mean by atrial fibrillation.
So what we're going to try
to do now is to detect it.
So we're going to
take data like that
and try to classify it into a
number of different categories.
Now this is something which
has been studied for decades,
and last year, 2017,
there was a competition
run by Professor Roger
Mark, who is here
at MIT, which is trying
to see, well, how could--
how good are we at
trying to figure out
which patients have different
types of heart rhythms
based on data that
looks like this?
So this is a normal
rhythm, which
is also called a sinus rhythm.
And over here it's atrial--
this is an example one patient
who has atrial fibrillation.
This is another type of rhythm
that's not atrial fibrillation,
but is abnormal.
And this is a noisy recording--
for example, if a patient's--
doesn't really have their
two fingers very well put
on to the two leads
of the device.
So given one of these
categories, can we predict--
one of these signals,
could predict
which category it came from?
So if you looked at
this, you might recognize
that they look a bit different.
So could some of
you guess what might
be predictive features
that differentiate
one of these signals
from the other?
In the back?
AUDIENCE: The
presence and absence
of one of the peaks the QRS
complex are [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: So
speak in English
for people who don't know
what these terms mean.
AUDIENCE: There is one
large piece, which can--
probably we can consider one
mV and there is another peak,
which is sort of like--
they have reverse polarity
between normal rhythm
and [INAUDIBLE].
DAVID SONTAG: Good.
So are you a cardiologist?
AUDIENCE: No.
DAVID SONTAG: No, OK.
So what the student
suggested is one
could look for sort
of these inversions
to try to describe it a
little bit differently.
So here you're suggesting
the lack of those inversions
is predictive of
an abnormal rhythm.
What about another feature
that could be predictive?
Yep?
AUDIENCE: The spacing
between the peaks
is more irregular with the AF.
DAVID SONTAG: The
spacing between beats
is more irregular
with the AF rhythm.
So you're sort of
looking at this.
You see how here
this spacing is very
different from this spacing.
Whereas in the normal
rhythm, sort of the spacing
looks pretty darn regular.
All right, good.
So if I was to show you
40 examples of these
and then ask you to
classify some new ones,
how well do you think
you'll be able to do?
Pretty well?
I would be surprised if
you couldn't do reasonably
well at least distinguishing
between normal rhythm and AF
rhythm, because there seem to be
some pretty clear signals here.
Of course, as you get
into alternatives,
then the story gets
much more complex.
But let me dig in
a little bit deeper
into what I mean by this.
So let's define
some of these terms.
Well, cardiologists have studied
this for a really long time,
and they have-- so
what I'm showing
you here is one heart cycle.
And they've-- you can put names
to each of the peaks that you
would see in a regular heart
cycle-- so that-- for example,
that very high peak is
known as the R peak.
And you could look at, for
example, the interval--
so this is one beat.
You could look at the interval
between the R peak of one beat
and the R peak of
another peak, and define
that to be the RR interval.
In a similar way,
one could take--
one could find different
distinctive elements
of the signal--
by the way, each--
each time step
corresponds to the heart
being in a different position.
For a healthy heart, these
are relatively deterministic.
And so you could look at
other distances and derive
features from those
distances, as well,
just like we were talking
about, both within a beat
and across beats.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: So what's
the difference
between a segment and
an interval again?
DAVID SONTAG: I don't
know what the difference
between a segment
and an interval is.
Does anyone else know?
I mean, I guess the
interval is between probably
the heads of peaks, whereas
segments might refer to
within a interval.
That's my guess.
Does someone know better?
For the purpose
of today's class,
that's a good enough
understanding.
The point is this
is well understood.
One could derive
features from this.
AUDIENCE: By us.
DAVID SONTAG: By us.
So what would a traditional
approach be to this problem?
So this is--
I'm pulling this figure
from a paper from 2002.
What it'll do is it'll
take in that signal.
It'll do some filtering of it.
Then it'll run a peak
detection logic, which
will find these
peaks, and then it'll
measure intervals between
these peaks and within a beat.
And it'll take
those computations
or make some
decision based on it.
So that's a
traditional algorithm,
and they work pretty reasonably.
And so what do I mean
by signal processing?
Well, this is an
example of that.
I encourage any of you to go
home today and try to code up
a peaked finding algorithm.
It's not that hard, at
least not to get an OK one.
You might imagine
keeping a running tab
of what's the highest
signal you've seen so far.
Then you look to see what
is the first time it drops,
and the second time-- and the
next time it goes up larger
than, let's say, the previous--
suppose that one of--
you want to look for when the
drop is-- the maximum value--
recent maximum
value divided by 2.
And then you-- then you reset.
And you can imagine in this
way very quickly coding up
a peak finding algorithm.
And so this is just,
again, to give you
some intuition behind what a
traditional approach would be.
And then you can very
quickly see that that--
once you start to look at
some intervals between peaks,
that alone is often good
enough for predicting
whether a patient has
atrial fibrillation.
So this is a figure
taken from paper in 2001
showing a single
patient's time series.
So the x-axis is for
that single patient,
their heart beats across time.
The y-axis is just
showing the RR interval
between the previous beat
and the current beat.
And down here in the
bottom is the ground truth
of whether the patient
is assessed to have--
to be in-- to have a normal
rhythm or atrial fibrillation,
which is noted as this
higher value here.
So these are AF rhythms.
This is normal.
This is AF again.
And what you can see is that
the RR interval actually
gets you pretty far.
You notice how it's
pretty high up here.
Suddenly it drops.
The RR interval
drops for a while,
and that's when
the patient has AF.
Then it goes up again.
Then it drops again, and so on.
And so it's not deterministic,
the relationship,
but there's definitely a lot
of signal just from that.
So you might say,
OK, well, what's
the next thing we could do
to try to clean up the signal
a little bit more?
So flash backwards from 2001 to
1970 here at MIT, studied by--
actually, no, this is not MIT.
This is somewhere else, sorry.
But still 1970-- where they
used a Markov model very
similar to the Markov models
we were just talking about
in the previous example to model
what a sequence of normal RR
intervals looks like versus
what a sequence of abnormal,
for example, AF RR
intervals looks like.
And in that way,
one can recognize
that, for any one
observation of an RR interval
might not by itself be
perfectly predictive,
but if you look at sort
of a sequence of them
for a patient with
atrial fibrillation,
there is some common
pattern to it.
And you can-- one can detect it
by just looking at likelihood
of that sequence under each
of these two different models,
normal and abnormal.
And that did pretty well--
even better than the previous
approaches for--
for predicting
atrial fibrillation.
This is the paper I
wanted to say from MIT.
Now 1991, this is also
from Roger Mark's group.
Now this is a neural network
based approach, where it says,
OK, we're going to take
a bunch of these things.
We're going to derive a
bunch of these intervals,
and then we're going to throw
that through a black box
supervised machine
learning algorithm
to predict whether a
patient has AF or not.
So these are very--
first of all, there are
some simple approaches here
that work reasonably well.
Using neural networks in this
domain is not a new thing,
but where are we as a field?
So as I mentioned, there was
this competition last year,
and what I'm showing
you here-- the citation
is from one of the
winning approaches.
And this winning approach
really brings the two paradigms
together.
It extracts a large number
of expert derived features--
so shown here.
And these are exactly
the types of things
you might think, like
proportion, median RR
interval of regular rhythms,
max RR irregularity measure.
And there's just a whole
range of different things
that you can imagine manually
deriving from the data.
And you throw all
of these features
into a machine
learning algorithm,
maybe a random forest, maybe a
neural network, doesn't matter.
And what you get out is a
slightly better algorithm
than what if you
had just come up
with a simple rule on your own.
That was the winning
algorithm then.
And in the summary paper, they
conjectured that, well, maybe
it's the case that they were--
they'd expected that
convolutional neural networks
would win.
And they were surprised that
none of the winning solutions
involved convolution
neural networks.
And they conjectured that may be
the reason why is because maybe
with these 8,000 patients
that they had [INAUDIBLE] that
just wasn't enough to give the
more complex models advantage.
So flip forward now to
this year and the article
that you read in your
readings in Nature Medicine,
where the Stanford
group now showed
how a convolutional neural
network approach, which
is, in many ways, extremely
naive-- all it does
is it takes the
sequence data in.
It makes no attempt at trying
to understand the underlying
physiology, and just
predicts from that--
can do really, really well.
And so there are
couple of differences
that I want to emphasize
to the previous work.
First, the censor is different.
Whereas the previous work
used this alive core censor,
in this paper from
Stanford, they're
using a different censor
called the Zio patch, which
is attached to the human
body and conceivably
much less noisy.
So that's one big difference.
The second big difference
is that there's dramatically
more data.
Instead of 8,000
patients to train from,
now they have over
90,000 records
from 50,000 different
patients to train from.
The third major
difference is that now,
rather than just trying to
classify into four categories--
normal, abnormal,
other, or noisy--
now we're going
to try to classify
into 14 different categories.
We're, in essence, breaking
apart that other class
into much finer grain
detail of different types
of abnormal rhythms.
And so here are some of
those other abnormal rhythms,
things like complete
heart block,
and a bunch of other
names I can't pronounce.
And from each one of these,
they gathered a lot of data.
And that actually did--
so it's not described
in the paper,
but I've talked to
the authors, and they
did-- they gathered this data
in a very interesting way.
So they sort of-- they did
their training iteratively.
They looked to see
where their errors were,
and then they went and gathered
more data from patients
with that subcategory.
So many of these
other categories
are very under-- might
be underrepresented
in the general population,
but they actually
gather a lot of
patients of that type
in their data set for
training purposes.
And so I think those
three things ended up
making a very big difference.
So what is their
convolutional network?
Well, first of all,
it's a 1-D signal.
So it's a little bit
different from the con nets
you typically see
in computer vision,
and I'll show you an
illustration of that
in the next slide.
It's a very deep model.
So it's 34 layers.
So the input comes in on the
very top in this picture.
It's passed through
a number of layers.
Each layer consists of
convolution followed
by rectified linear
units, and there is sub
sampling at every
other layer so that you
go from a very wide signal--
so a very long--
I can't remember how long--
1 second long signal
summarized down
into sort of much-- just many
smaller number of dimensions,
which you then have a sort
of fully connected layer
at the bottom to do
for your predictions.
And then they also have
these shortcut connections,
which allow you to pass
information from earlier layers
down to the very
end of the network,
or even into
intermediate layers.
And for those of you who
are familiar with residual
networks, it's the same idea.
So what is a 1D convolution?
Well, it looks a
little bit like this.
So this is the signal.
I'm going to just approximate
it by a bunch of 1's and 0's.
I'll say this is a 1.
This is a 0.
This is a 1, 1, so on.
A convolutional network has
a filter associated with it.
That filter is then
applied in a 1D model.
It's applied in
a linear fashion.
It's just taken a dot product
with the filter's values,
with the values of the
signal at each point in time.
So it looks a little
bit like this,
and this is what you get out.
So this is the convolution
of a single filter
with the whole signal.
And the computation I did
there-- so for example,
this first number came
from taking the dot product
of the first three numbers--
1, 0, 1-- with the filter.
So it's 1 times 2 plus 3 times
0 plus 1 times 1, which is 3.
And so each of the
subsequent numbers
was computed in the same way.
And I usually have you figure
out what this last one is,
but I'll leave that
for you to do at home.
And that's what a
1D convolution is.
And so they have-- they do this
for lots of different filters.
Each of those filters might
be of varying lengths,
and each of those will
detect different types
of signal patterns.
And in this way, after
having many layers of these,
one can, in an
automatic fashion,
extract many of the same types
of signals used in that earlier
work, but also be much
more flexible to detect
some new ones, as well.
Hold your question,
because I need to wrap up.
So in the paper
that you read, they
talked about how
they evaluated this.
And so I'm not going to go
into much depth in it now.
I just want to point out
two different metrics
that they used.
So the first metric
they used was
what they called a
sequential error metric.
What that looked at is you
had this very long sequence
for each patient, and
they labeled different one
second intervals
of that sequence
into abnormal,
normal, and so on.
So you could ask,
how good are we
at labeling each of
the different points
along the sequence?
And that's the sequence metric.
The different-- the second
metric is the set metric,
and that looks at,
if the patient has
something that's abnormal
anywhere, did you detect it?
So that's, in essence,
taking an or of
each of those 1
second intervals,
and then looking
across patients.
And from a clinical
diagnostic perspective,
the set metric might be
most useful, but then
when you want to
introspect and understand
where is that happening,
then the sequential metric is
important.
And the key take home message
from the paper is that,
if you compared the model's
predictions-- this is, I think,
using an f1 metric--
to what you would get from
a panel of cardiologists,
these models are doing as well,
if not better than these panels
of cardiologists.
So this is extremely exciting.
This is technology--
or variance of this
is technology that you're
going to see deployed now.
So for those of you who have
purchased these Apple watches,
these Samsung watches, I don't
know exactly what they're
using, but I
wouldn't be surprised
if they're using
techniques similar to this.
And you're going to see much
more of that in the future.
So this is going to be
really the first example
in this course so
far of something
that's really been deployed.
And so in summary,
we're very often
in the realm of not enough data.
And in this lecture today,
we gave two examples
how you can deal with that.
First, you can try to use
mechanistic and statistical
models to try to work
in settings where
you don't have much data.
And in other extremes,
you do have a lot of data,
and you can try to
ignore that, and just
use these black box approaches.
That's all for today.